<?xml version="1.0"?>
<actions>
    <action type="python" id="fetch_water_data">
        <content>
import requests
import datetime
import json

station_id = "28B080"
data_types = ["DSG", "STG", "WTM", "ATM"]
current_year = datetime.datetime.now().year
start_year = current_year - 1

all_data = {}

for data_type in data_types:
    all_data[data_type] = {}
    # Fetch current data
    current_url = f"https://apps.ecology.wa.gov/ContinuousFlowAndWQ/StationData/Prod/{station_id}/{station_id}_{data_type}_FM.TXT"
    try:
        print("current_url")
        print(current_url)
        response = requests.get(current_url, timeout=10)
        response.raise_for_status()
        all_data[data_type]["current"] = response.text
    except requests.exceptions.RequestException as e:
        print(f"Error fetching current {data_type} data: {e}")
        all_data[data_type]["current"] = f"Error: {e}"

    # Fetch historical data for the last 10 years
    all_data[data_type]["historical"] = {}
    for year in range(start_year, current_year):
        historical_url = f"https://apps.ecology.wa.gov/ContinuousFlowAndWQ/StationData/Prod/{station_id}/{station_id}_{year}_{data_type}_FM.TXT"
        try:
            print("historical_url")
            print(historical_url)
            response = requests.get(historical_url, timeout=10)
            response.raise_for_status()
            all_data[data_type]["historical"][year] = response.text
        except requests.exceptions.RequestException as e:
            print(f"Error fetching historical {data_type} {year} data: {e}")
            all_data[data_type]["historical"][year] = f"Error: {e}"

# Print all data to standard output for gemini to use. Using json for proper formatting/parsing.
print(json.dumps(all_data))
</content>
    </action>

    <action type="reasoning" id="synthesize_report" model="google/gemini-2.0-flash-001" depends_on="fetch_water_data">
        <content>
You are a water quality expert. You have been provided with data from a water monitoring station.
Your job is to generate a concise report discussing the current and historical trends for different water parameters. Focus on critical observations and actionable insights.

The station ID is 28B080.  The data covers the last 10 years.
The following parameters are logged:
DSG: Discharge/Stream Gage
STG: Stage/Gage height
WTM: Water Temperature
ATM: Air Temperature

Data is provided in the following JSON format:
```json
{{outputs.fetch_water_data.raw_response}}
```

Each datapoint is the literal text retrieved from the Washington State Department of Ecology website when it is queried for station ID 28B080. The data is a dictionary where:
- Keys are data types (DSG, STG, WTM, ATM).
- Each data type has "current" and "historical" keys.
- "current" holds the latest data.
- "historical" holds data for each year over the last 10 years.

Your report must include but is not limited to:

1.  **Executive Summary:** Briefly summarize key findings and any significant concerns.
2.  **Current Readings Analysis:**
    *   State the most recent readings for each parameter (DSG, STG, WTM, ATM).
    *   Identify any readings that deviate significantly from expected values or historical norms and warrant further investigation. Explain *why* they are concerning.
3.  **Historical Trend Analysis (Last 10 Years):**
    *   Describe the overall trends for each parameter (DSG, STG, WTM, ATM).  Are they increasing, decreasing, or stable?
    *   Highlight any notable patterns, anomalies, or significant fluctuations in the historical data.
    *   Avoid simply stating the data; provide meaningful interpretation (e.g., "Water temperature has been steadily increasing over the past decade, potentially impacting aquatic life.").
4.  **Community Impact:**
    *   Explain how the station's data can be valuable to the community.
    *   Provide specific examples of how the data can be used for informed decision-making, resource management, or public awareness (e.g., "This data can help local farmers optimize irrigation practices," or "The data can be used to alert the community to potential flood risks.").

**Conciseness:** Keep the report brief and to the point. Focus on the most important information.
**Actionable Insights:** Prioritize insights that lead to potential actions or further investigation.
        </content>
    </action>

    <action type="python" id="save_report" depends_on="synthesize_report">
        <content>
import datetime

try:
    report = outputs["synthesize_report"]["raw_response"]
    timestamp = datetime.datetime.now().strftime("%Y-%m-%d_%H-%M-%S")
    filename = f"water_station_report_{timestamp}.md"

    with open(filename, "w") as f:
        f.write(f"# Water Station Report (Station ID: 28B080) - {timestamp}\n\n{report}")

    print(f"Report saved to {filename}")
except Exception as e:
    print(f"Error saving report: {e}")
</content>
    </action>
</actions>